Guide to the Carolee Schneemann Papers M1892
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 2. Project binders
  - Cooking with Apes [B/N #28], 1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Approximately 20 pages of typescript with extensive holograph corrections, including the text of the American I Ching Apple Pie. Includes approximately 25 images, contact sheets and negative strips, 4x5 negative, articles, ephemera.
  - Cycladic Imprints [B/N #29], 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    Correspondence with San Francisco Museum of Modern Art regarding the multimedia installation as well as press release, about 20 color and black and white negatives, contact sheets, about 5 transparencies, over 70 black and white photographs and color slides.
  - Cycladic Imprints [B/N #30], 1988-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Sketches for Cycladic Imprints installation, contact sheets, black and white negatives, strips of 35 mm black and white negatives, 5 strips of 35 mm color negatives, 14 color photographs, 31 color negatives, 40 black and white photographs, watercolor sketches for the installation, letter to Elliot Elgart of UCLA Art Department, copies of notes and performance instructions, clippings, 31 slides, original drawings.
  - Cycladic Slides [B/N #31], 1992 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    180 numbered slides (160 numbered; 20 Cincinnati installation). These are duplicates of slide trays MISC #6-7.
  - Dirty Pictures [B/N #32] (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Performance notes and sketches.
  - Dirty Pictures [B/N #33] (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    Typescript notes for the exhibition/workshop, with minor holograph corrections and revisions. More than 100 photographs, of various sizes, approximately two hundred slides, contact sheets, negative strips, various ephemera. Some contact sheets removed to oversize folder.
  - Dirty Pictures contact sheets [B/N #33] (Box 140, Folder 10)
  - Dirty Pictures Formative Dirty Pictures [B/N #34] (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Approximately 200 pages of typescript with extensive holograph revisions and drawings. Approximately 100 pages of typescript and holograph notes on the rehearsal for the performance. Also includes approximately five 8 1/2" x 11" photographs, and 20 numbered slides, original drawings, fliers
  - Double Trouble [B/N #35], 2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Newspaper clippings, over 30 color negatives, about 90 color slides, and about 40 color photographs.
  - Drawings and Peformances [B/N #36], 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Over 40 annotated sketches and watercolors diagraming performances and stage sets including Apple I-Ching Pie and Water Light/Water Needle.
  - Dream Space Object [B/N #37], 1980s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Lecture material, 1 color photograph and 20 color slides.
  - Early Work and Portraits of Carolee from various periods [B/N #38] (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Over 20 strips of black and white negatives and contact sheets.
  - Exhibitions [B/N #40], 1970s-1980s (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
    Notes, press releases, about 40 color slides, approx. 125 photographs of various sizes depicting gallery installations, openings, Carolee at work, art works, etc., 6 strips of 35 mm color negatives; 6 strips of 2 3/4 cm color negatives, and contact sheets. Some photography by James M. Brown.
  - Expansions Naked Action Lecture [B/N #41], 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Images of the performance, with accompanying negatives, contact sheet, original cast list flier.
  - Eye Body Master Negative Binder [B/N #43], 1963-1976 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    Various negatives and prints of the Eye Body project. It is accompanied by Carolee's memoir written in 1976 explaining the project. The binder contains 33 color and 2 black and white slides depicting both herself and her artworks, about 10 strips of regular negatives, 20 large (3 1/2 cm) negatives and about 10 extra large (8" x 10") negatives. The binder also contains about 30 contact sheets and about 80 black and white photographs ranging in size from 3 1/2" x 5' and 6 1/2" x 10" to 8" x 10". Photographers include Leo Choplin, Alex Sobelewski, Erro.
  - Film As Art [B/N #44], 1996 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    Images of the exhibition. Approximately 40 images of various sizes, including color slides.
  - Fresh Blood [B/N #45], 1981-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Notes, images and ephemera surrounding Fresh Blood. Approximately 100 pages of typescript notes and letters in all, with with minor holograph revisions to the exhibition notes.
  - Fresh Blood [B/N #46], 1981-1986 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    Approximately 100 images of various sizes, 30 contact sheets, and photocopied typescript artist statements.
  - Friends Travel [B/N #47], 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 1-8)
    Approx. 1,200 mostly color slides and about 10 black and white transparencies.
  - Fuses [B/N #48] (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    Negatives, color and black and white photographs of various sizes, about 30 strips of color and black and white negatives, contact sheets, collage from photographs.
  - Ghost Rev [B/N #49], 1965 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Iinstructions for the installations, journal clippings, photographs (about 20 black and white 8" x 10"), negatives (about 7 strips), and contact sheets. Some photographs by Peter Moore and Ted Wester.
  - History Slides [B/N #50], 1950s-1960s (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Approximately 300 slides, half of which are labelled.
  - Home Run Muse [B/N #51], 1977 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    Approximately 200 pages of typescript with moderate holograph revisions, images, contact sheets, slides, and negatives, organized chronologically.
  - Home Run Muse [B/N #52], 1977 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Approximately 75 photographs of the exhibition, including like number of contact sheets and negative strips. Plus notes, texts, scores, reviews.
  - Illinois Central [B/N #54], 1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Stage directions, clippings, about 60 color and black and white slides, over 60 black and white photographs ranging from cut down nonstandard sizes to 2 1/4" x 3 1/4" and 8" x10", contact sheets, over 100 strips of black and white negatives, copies of correspondence. Contains an envelop with small photographs of landscapes. Photographs by Art Sinsabaugh.
  - Illinois Central [B/N #55], 1968 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    Stage instructions with sketches and over 70 black and white photographs, mostly by Art Sinsabaugh.
  - Illinois Landscapes [B/N #56], 1968 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    About 90 slides by Art Sinsabaugh.
  - Installations, Events, Works [B/N #58], 1980-2000 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Approximately 75 slides, images of various sizes, and reproductions highlighting works from 1980 onward.
  - Inverted Scroll + Cave [B/N #59], 1975, 1993 (Box 12, Folder 5-6)
    Approximately 50 prints of various sizes, with accompanying contact sheets and negatives. Includes photocopied text to adjoin the images.
  - Isis Ice [B/N #60], 1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Approximately 35 negative strips, several contact sheets, and approximately 30 photographs (photocopies) of the performance by Anthony McCall.
  - Judson Dance Theater: Lateral Splay and Queen's Dog [B/N #62], 1962-1983 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    Sketches and notes, 10 strips of negatives, 6 color slides for the 1983 revival, about 5 contact sheets and about 10 black and white photographs (8" x 10"). Photos are by Peter Moore, Charles Rotenberg and others.
  - Kitch's Last Meal [B/N #63] (Box 13, Folder 3-4)
    Clippings, annotated copy of an article about the film, project information, contact sheets, over 70 black and white photographs of various sizes, notes and cue cards about sound editing, over 40 strips of black and white negatives, 4 color and black and white transparencies of various sizes, notes and sketches for the film, color slides.
  - Kitch's Last Meal [B/N #64], 2003 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Annotated transcript of sound dialogues in Kitch's Last Meal.
  - Known/Unknown: Plague Column [B/N #65], 1996 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    Text for the 1996 exhibition, with moderate holograph corrections to the text. Also included are images from the installation and various press clippings.
  - Known/Unknown: Plague Column [B/N #66], 1995-1996 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Approximately 15 images, as well as the text used for the exhibition.
  - Loans-Losses-Returns [B/N #68] (Box 14, Folder 2)
    List of books stolen from Carolee in 1970, clippings, notes and correspondence and contracts about art work on loan; copies of letters sent by Traub and Yassky Attorneys at Law regarding the distribution of Fuses.
  - Loft End of It [B/N #69], 2003 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Over 60 color slides and 23 color photographs.
  - Imaging Her Erotics Manuscript [B/N #69], 2000 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
    With annotations, copies of correspondence between Carolee and John Isaacs and others.
  - Master Review Booklet [B/N #71] (Box 14, Folder 6)
    Reproductions of reviews.
  - Meat Joy [B/N #72], 1964 (Box 14, Folder 7, Box 15, Folder 1)
    Manuscripts, photographs, 55 black and white photographs (8" x 10"), transparencies, contact sheets, 20 strips of black and white negatives, 3 color negatives. Some of the photos are by F. Massal (Paris).
  - Meat Joy [B/N #73], 1964 (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
    Over 140 b&w photographs ranging in size from 5" x 7" to 8" x 10", 35 color photographs (3" x 4 1/2"), about 20 contact sheets, 20 black and white strips of negatives (3" x 2 1/2"), more than 10 color transparencies (4" x 5"), 6 slides with preparatory sketches. Binder includes transparencies with names of photographers. Photographs by Al Giese, P. Moore, Charles Rotenberg, H. Zucker, and others.
  - Meat Joy Slides [B/N #74], 1964 (Box 15, Folder 6, Box 16, Folder 1)
    33 slide sleeves with about 550 color and black and white slides.
  - Meat Systems [B/N #75], 1970 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    Approximately 35 slides, several images of the demonstration, and accompanying ephemera.
  - Meat Joy - Whitechapel Art Gallery [B/N #76], 2002 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Over 60 color photographs (4" x 6") and about 80 color slides.
  - MIT Design Photos [B/N #77] (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Reproductions of "Proto-Feminist Body" chapter.
  - Moon in a Tree (Cornell) [B/N #78], circa 1972 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Approximately 100 pages of autograph notes for lectures on Joseph Cornell after his death. Included are photocopies of correspondence between Schneemann and Cornell.
  - More Wrong Things [B/N #79], circa 1972 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Over 30 color transparencies, annotated typescripts, about 100 color slides, over 30 color photographs of various sizes, and press releases.
  - Mortal Coils [B/N #80], 1994 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    About 40 slides documenting the set up of the installation, images and bios of 15 friends who died, press release from Penine Hart Gallery.
  - Mortal Coils [B/N #81], 1997 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
    Color slides of the exhibition. Approximately 19 25 4x6" detail images of the exhibition, and several 8.5x11" images of the installation. Included are various ephemera, press clippings, and short biographies of the subjects (fifteen friends who passed in 1993). Also included are approximately 100 4x6" photographs of the accompanying reception.
  - Negatives B+W, Paintings, Installations, Body [B/N #82], 1960s-1990s (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
    About 10 color slides, about 20 10 color and black and white photographs of various sizes, about 50 transparencies of various sizes, over 60 color and black and white negatives, contact sheets. Photographs by George Hirose, Dan Chichester.
  - Mortal Coils Negs, Slides, B+W [B/N #83], late 1990s (Box 248)
    About 70 color and black and white photographs of various sizes, black and white transparencies, color slides, black and white negatives, contact sheets, notes and explanations, and gallery brochure regarding the "Mortal Coils" project and its installation. Binder also contains information about a memorial service for Charlotte Moorman.
  - Nieman Edit - Film Book [B/N #84], 1970s (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Misc. notes and reproductions such as photographs, artcles, artist statements, film notes.
  - Night Crawlers - Expo Montreal [B/N #85], 1968 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Clippings, news releases, about 7 black and white photographs, about 6 black and white negative strips, black and white transparency (3 3/4" x 5"), and contact sheets. Photographs by Shunk-Kender.
  - Known/Unknown: Plague Column [B/N #86], 1968 (Box 18, Folder 3-4)
    Approximately 350 color slides of the exhibition, and approximately 35 photos of varying sizes from 8 1/2 x 11" to 4-6". Includes photocopies and ephemera surrounding the exhibition, also various notes from Galerie Samuel Lallouz containing packing list, bills and receipts regarding the installation.
  - Nude [B/N #87], 1960-1996 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
    Collection of nude photographs, including Schneemann's appearance in Caterpillar magazine, including original negatives. Approximately three hundred photographs of various sizes, and approximately 50 slides. (PLUS: negatives, ephemera, large negatives, letter from Fred McDarrah)
  - Manipulations/Ordeals [B/N #88], 1967-1969 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Clippings, performance instructions, 15 black and white 8 x 10 photographs, 15 strips of original negatives and 4 contact sheets. Photographs by Peter Moore.
  - Out of Actions [B/N #89], 1997-1999 (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
    Approximately 100 photographs, ranging in size between 3x5" and 8 1/2x11", of the installation, several pages of autograph notes on the construction, and approximately 57 75 color slides. Also includes various ephemera surrounding the exhibition, 2x2 color negatives.
  - Owl Ocean Table [B/N #90], 1985 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Color and black and white photographs (some taped together to create a panoramic view), notes, script, clippings about birds, stage notes with sketches, correspondence with Johanna Demetrakas, 17 color slides.
  - Painting Constructions [B/N #91], 1960s (Box 19, Folder 5-7)
    Press releases related to Max Hutchinson Gallery, color reproductions, collage for "Concretion Collage" flier, over 70 black and white and color photographs of artworks (various sizes), 4 color transparencies. Some photographs by Eric Pollitzer.
  - Painting Constructions Master Set-Slides [B/N #92], 1953-late 1980s (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    Approximately 400 color and black and white slides of artworks and happenings and 3 strips of negatives.
  - Photo Negs and Contacts [B/N #95], 1976-1985 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    Contact sheets and about 170 color and black and white negatives, 4 b&w photos & 2 color images.
  - Plagiarism, Telepathy or Forgetful Borrowings? [B/N #96] (Box 20, Folder 4-6)
    Images of Carolee's work and that of other artists, agencies, etc that have similar qualities such as composition, medium, objects, themes.
  - Plumb Line [B/N #97], 1968 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Contact sheets, reproductions, about 50 black and white photographs of different sizes, over 20 strips of black and white negatives, about 5 transparencies, "Plumb Line" manuscript, contact sheets, and Carolee's filmography.
  - Preparations for Mortal Coils [B/N #98] (Box 247)
    Newspaper clippings, biographical notes about friends, over 50 artist's manuscripts, color sketches and comments for the installation, about 40 color and black and white photographs of various sizes, about 5 transparencies.
  - Round House [B/N #99], 1967 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    Several negative strips and accompanying contact prints, approximately 35 images of the performance and rehearsals, articles, score, photocopies.
  - Round House and Thames Crawling [B/N #100], 1970 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Approximately 200 pages of photocopied notes concerning the two exhibitions.
  - Schlaget Auf, Ices Strip [B/N #101], 1970, 1971 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    Approximately 50 images of varying sizes of both exhibitions. Includes several contact sheets and negative strips, as well as a quarto-sized notebook with holograph notes on both exhibitions and two original photographs taken of Schlager Auf by Hermann Kiessling.
  - Scroll Paintings with Exploded TV [B/N #102], 1991 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Approximately 20 black and white images of the exhibition, and several contact sheets. Also included are slides and a poster advertisement for the show.
  - Selected Works Survey [B/N #103] (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Prospectus sent to the Montreal Museum of Fine Arts.
  - Site [B/N #104], 1964 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    18 color slides, 2 strips of black and white negatives, 2 black and white photographs, 2 color photographs (3" x 4 1/2") by Namuth. Photographs, including that of Carolee and Rauschenberg in his kitchen by Hans Namuth.
  - Slide Groups [B/N #105], 1964 (Box 22, Folder 4-5)
    Collected slides, images, contact sheets, and negatives surrounding four exhibitions: Enter Vulva, Ask the Goddess, Skewed Beams, Art is Reactionary.
  - Small Photos and Negs. Work Model Performed [B/N #106], 1964 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Contact sheets, black and white negatives (about 14 strips), color slides (4), over 300 color and black and white photographs depicting performances, lectures, art works and friends.
  - Snows [B/N #107], 1967 (Box 23, Folder 1-3)
    About 100 black and white photographs ranging in size from 3 1/2" x 5" and 8" x 10", 2 color photographs ranging in size from 1/2" x 5" and 8" x 10", contact sheets, about 10 marker and pencil sketches, about 45 color and black and white slides, color and black and white negatives, stage notes Photographs by Ted Wester, Charlotte Victoria, A.V. Sobolewski, Peter Moore.
  - Teaching Black and White [B/N #108] (Box 23, Folder 4-5)
    Approximately 50 images, as well as slides used for teaching. Plus negatives, contact sheets, notes, scores, texts, student drawings.
  - Teaching-Slides photo copies [B/N #109] (Box 24, Folder 1)
    Over 50 color photographs and about 60 color slides. Names mentioned include Sands Murray-Wassink, Marjanel Ragen Murray, Andrea Sulzer.
  - The Environment for Sound and Motion [B/N #110], 1962 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Color slides, contact sheets, newspaper clippings, notes, one strip of negatives and about 10 photographs.
  - Unexpectedly Research [B/N #113], 1963-1982 (Box 24, Folder 3-4)
    Several hundred images made or performed between 1963 and 1982. Included are several hand-colored original prints, and several pages of negatives. Also included are related ephemera, from plans for the exhibition to press clippings and statements from the artist. Plus 2 hand-made collages of photogrid layout; 49 slides, color negatives by Nathalie Legault.
  - Up to and Including Her Limits [B/N #114], 1973-1976 (Box 24, Folder 5-6)
    Images of various sizes detailing the performance, including approximately 50 contact sheets and negative strips. Also includes various ephemera concerning the exhibitions, slides, large negatives.
  - Various [B/N #115], 1962-1967 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Various images and notes on five early exhibitions: Looseleaf (1962), Originale (1964), Noise Bodies (1965), Push Pull (1965) and Night Crawlers (1967). Includes photocopied typescripts of notes and descriptions of each performance/exhibition, images of various sizes, contact sheets, negatives, & orginial drawings.
  - Vespers Pool [B/N #119], 2000 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    About 80 slides.
  - Vulva's Morphia [B/N #121], 1997 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    Reproductions of all Vulva plates and text.
  - Vulva's Morphia [B/N #122], 1993-1996 (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
    Approximately 200 color slides, and approximately 100 photographs of various sizes. Also included here are several diagrams of the exhibition, with numbers for corresponding images in the layout, as well as folders containing notes and ephemera, most notably typescripts of text used in the exhibition.
  - Water Light/Water Needle [B/N #123], 1966 (Box 25, Folder 6, Box 26, Folder 1-2)
    Performance program, about 75 slides, about 100 black and white photographs ranging from 6 3/4" x 7" to 8" x 10", black and white transparencies, 20 color photographs (3" x 4 1/2"), contact sheets, over 20 strips of black and white negatives, color transparency. Photographs by Herbert Migdoll, Mah Wah, C. Victoria. 5 strips of 8mm color film removed to oversize folder.
  - Water Light/Water Needle film [B/N #123] (Box 140, Folder 11)
  - Waterville Floods (Colby College [B/N #124], 1968 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    Stage instructions, script, with James Tenney divorce contract (Oct 9, 1968), contact sheets and 4 strips of black and white negatives.
  - Women in Photography -- Lecture [B/N #125], 1992 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    Notes for Schneemann's 1992 lecture "The Delirious Arousal of Destruction: Or, is there a Feminist Erotic Iconography?" Included are approximately 40 fluxus-related images, and 16 slides.
  - Selected Works Survey binder [B/N #126], 2009 (Box 124, Folder 5)
  - Shoots by Fred McDarrah [B/N #127] (Box 26, Folder 5)
    Photocopies.
- Series 3. Project ephemera
  Instructions, inventories, performance notes, gallery guides and other material concerning performances, installations and exhibitions.
  - Film/Video Inventory - Loft [M11], 2002 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Saw Over Want - Vulva [M19] (Box 28, Folder 3)
    Reproductions for Vulva and other installations.
  - Artwork - Installation & Instructions [A2], 1998 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    6 color diagrams of misc. installations with directions regarding equipment, lighting, etc.
  - Known/Unknown: Plague Column [M12], 1996-1997 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    Prospectus for the exhibition, including various reproductions of images and text.
  - Fresh Blood/Venus Vectors [photographs, layouts, notes, performance texts, etc.] (Box 125, Folder 2-7)
  - performance texts [scripts/notes on index cards] (Flat-box 128)
  - exhibition lists/inventories, 1961-1963 (Box 62, Folder 4)
    Also includes several pages from guest registry for a May 1963 Machin-Schneemann-Steinmann group show in New York City, with signatures from Robert Rauschenberg, Ray Johnson, Philip Corner, Aaron Siskind, Jonas Mekas, Yvonne Rainier, Allan Kaprow (with brief note), Susan Sontag, Claes Oldenberg, George Brecht, and many others.
  - Up to & Including Her Limits [B11] (Box 134, Folder 1)
    11" x 9" maquette for the catalogue, with comments and drawings by Schneemann, approx 30pp.
  - Installation Instructions [A3], 1968-1980s (Box 134, Folder 2)
    24pp., sketch pad (14" x 17") with drawings, instructions and comments about various happenings and installations.
  - exhibition production book, 1983 (Box 140, Folder 7)
  - ABC We Print Anything cards [IC1] (Box 143)
    "Cards stolen - Incomplete edition." Purple cloth box containing an incomplete set (56/151) of cards displayed at Whitebox Gallery around 2001; 8 out of 156 image cards went missing. The run contained 151 sets.
- Series 4. Correspondence, 1949-2011
  Personal and professional correspondence to and from Schneemann, the bulk of which is from the 1990s and 2000s. The series is arranged chronologically. Some are photocopies, especially for earlier years, and much of the series consists of drafts of CS outgoing letters. Postcards and holiday cards are separated. There are significant amounts of correspondence in other series, especially Project Files and Other Artists.
  - Joel Farber, 1949-1950 (Box 76, Folder 1)
  - 1953-1957 (Box 76, Folder 2)
    mosarly personal to and from Elsa. One to Jimpy And Al. Added Joanne, Alivia, Eve, Florence, Mari, family
  - CS to Naomi Levinson [originals and drafts], 1955-1956 (Box 108, Folder 8)
  - CS to Naomi Levinson [originals and drafts], 1957 (Box 108, Folder 9)
  - CS to Naomi Levinson [originals and drafts], 1958 (Box 108, Folder 10)
  - CS to Naomi Levinson [originals and drafts], 1959 (Box 108, Folder 11)
  - CS to Naomi Levinson [originals and drafts], 1960, 1962, 1976 (Box 109, Folder 1)
  - Naomi Levinson to CS, undated, 1955-1956 (Box 109, Folder 2)
  - Naomi Levinson to CS, 1957 (Box 109, Folder 3)